<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vniversall medicine: or The vertues of the antimoniall cup Collected out of the experiments, and observations of the most famous, learned, and best approved philosophers, and physicians, that have written of that subject. By Iohn Evans minister, and preacher of Gods Word.</title>
            <author>Evans, John, minister of Gods word.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10587</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855699</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855699</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21201</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00453)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21201)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1023:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vniversall medicine: or The vertues of the antimoniall cup Collected out of the experiments, and observations of the most famous, learned, and best approved philosophers, and physicians, that have written of that subject. By Iohn Evans minister, and preacher of Gods Word.</title>
                  <author>Evans, John, minister of Gods word.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>British Library copies have folding leaf, in 2 settings, beginning: "to the right honourable .. Nobility and Gentrie". They mention the book and have advertisement where Evans makes and sells the cups.--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Antimony --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="authors_oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:1"/>
            <head>To the right honourable and right worſhipfull the Nobility and Gentrie of Great Brittaine.</head>
            <p>WHereas the teſtimonies of learned Philoſophers and Phyſicians have given ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent aſſurance, that the Infuſion of the <hi>Antimoniall Cup</hi> is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall</hi> and <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Medicine,</hi> and that the Experiments of Honourable &amp; worthy Perſons have confirmed the ſame to be a wholſome and Prevalent Medicine againſt many dangerous and deſperate Diſeaſes, as by their ſeverall Certificats may appeare: And that (without unthankfulnes to the alone Giver of all good gifts, Injurie to the Common wealth, and offence againſt Chriſtian charity) it may not be concealed: my humble ſuit therefore is, to all (to whom theſe preſents ſhall come) that they would be pleaſed to peruſe the Authorities by me alledged in my booke called the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Medicine,</hi> and to afford me their friendly aſſiſtance for the better communication and declaration thereof for the health and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon benefit of mankind. And if any receive harme by the uſe thereof (following the directions of my booke) or if I report fraudulently of the <hi>Medicinall vertues</hi> thereof, let it be required at my hands both in this life and in that to come.</p>
            <p>The Antimoniall Cups herein mentioned are made and ſold by <hi>Iohn Evans</hi> Miniſter of Gods word dwelling in Gunpowder-Alley neere fetter lane.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Vniverſall Medicine: OR THE VERTVES OF THE <hi>Antimoniall Cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected out of the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Obſervations of the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, learned, and beſt approved Philoſophers, and Phyſicians, that have written of that Subject.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn Evans</hi> Miniſter, and Preacher of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joſ. Quer. cap. 31. pag. 386.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In hoc unico Antimonio videndam exhibebimus Vniverſalem Medicinam, Medicinarum Medicinam, &amp; admirandorum aut miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum ipſum miraculum, ſeu mirabile mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilium.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Haviland,</hi> 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat the Lord hath ſanctified, and communicated for the health and profit of many, ought not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed for the Envie &amp; displeaſure of a few: Gods candle muſt not be put under a buſhell, neither muſt his Talent be wrapped up, and buried in the ground: his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments are communicative, and everie reall Chriſtian may vendicate his part and portion therein. To you therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth this Medicinall Iemme, whoſoever that deſire to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent contagious, and infectious maladies, to preſerve your bodies in health, ſtrength, and vigor of Nature, or to reſtore ſuch as are already infirmed with desperate and dangerous diſeaſes. Accept then this excellent Iewell as the ſingular gift of God, and the Medicinall vertues thereof herein mentioned, for the approved experiments, of Right Honourable, and Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Perſonages, many of them for their Eminencie, and height of Honour, wherewith they are rightfully ennobled, not here to be mentioned: And the reſt of ſuch worth and dignitie, that for their pietie, &amp; learning, they are not inferior to many in the Kingdome. And although this might give ſufficient ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to all reaſonable mindes: Nevertheleſſe, for that an undoubted Truth, feareth not to be expoſed to all examinations, whoſoever pleaſeth, ſhall have a moneths triall of them before they buy them: To the end that by the certaintie of their owne knowledge, practice, and experience, they may be fully confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the one halfe of the medicinall vertues of this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall Cup, is not herein reported unto them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_virtues">
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:3"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the moſt admirable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of the Antimoniall Cup.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> It keepeth the body from repletion and fulneſſe of humors.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> It helpeth againſt all evill affects of the Stomacke.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> It cureth all intermitting Agues, and burning Fevers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> It helpeth the ſwimming in the head, Madneſſe, &amp; Frenzie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> It cureth the Greene Sickneſſe, and helpeth against all Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> It prevents the Stone, the Gout, and the Sciatica, and other Aches.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> It is a good Preſervative againſt all contagious and infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Diſeaſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> It cureth perfectly Morbus Gallious, and Lues <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enerea.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> It aſſwageth the Falling Sickneſſe, and all Convulſions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> It deſtroyeth wormes, and maketh complexion faire,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> It emptieth the Stomacke of ill humours: the Liver of Choler: the Spleene of Melancholy: the Pectorall parts of all hurtfull humours: The Head and the throat of flegme and rheume, and all diſtillations.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> It reſtoreth appetite loſt: it cauſeth reſt to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſenſes aend ſleepe, and loſeth not his vertue through uſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> It cureth wounds, and ſtancheth bloud.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> It taketh away Wens, and other Excreſcenſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> It cleanſeth, and healeth ulcerous Sores, and Fiſtulaes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> It conſumeth rotten, and putrified dead fleſh.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> It purifieth the ſight, and conſumeth the Web and Pearle.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> It is excellent againſt all Diſeaſes uſed in Clyſters.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19.</hi> It aſſwageth the paine of the Gout, or any other Ach, by bathing and externall application.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>See the Uſe in the Latter end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made, and are to be ſold by</hi> Iohn Evans, <hi>Miniſter and Preacher of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Word, dwelling neere Fetter-Lane, in Gun-powder Alley.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:3"/>
            <head>A CONFIRMATION of the Medicinall Vertues of the Antimoniall Cup Collected out of the moſt famous, learned, and beſt approved Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and Phyſicians, that have written thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all the Minerals contained within the bowels of the Earth, <hi>Antimonium</hi> deſerveth the greateſt praiſe, for the moſt excellent medicinall vertues, it containeth for the health and benefit of mankinde.</p>
            <p>It is a Minerall of a darke colour, interveined with gliſtering ſtreakes, conſiſting according to <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> of Mercurie, Sulphur, and Salt. <hi>Antimonium corpus ſuum ex Mercurio aſſumit, eſt que natura Mercurii craſſiſſima, poſtquam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgatur, vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s &amp; virtutes Mercurii omnes retinet, nihilque eſt aliud<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quam coagulatus Mercurius per ſpiritum Salis &amp; Sulphur.</hi> And therefore it is generally by all the Spagiricks called the Balſame, Reſtorer, and Preſerver of Nature.</p>
            <p>It was firſt diſcovered by <hi>Geber</hi> King of Arab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and by him called <hi>Magneſia,</hi> for as the <hi>Magnes</hi> draweth iron unto it with the one point, and expelleth it with the other; ſo this magnetically extracteth to, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth from the Stomack whatſoever within the whole body of man, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> found to be offenſive to Nature, or contrarie to the health and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the body.</p>
            <p>It is alſo called <hi>Lupus,</hi> for that it devoureth and deſtroyeth all metal-except the Lion, which is gold: and that it refineth and purifieth above all other things, ſo doth it alſo deſtroy all the corrupt humour, that are within the body of man, leaving no impuritie to remaine in the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſilius Valentinus Monachus,</hi> compareth it to a Ring without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, without ending, for that his medicinall and naturall vertues are inſcrutable and paſt finding out.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:4"/>
            <p>Many are the Medicines that are prepared of this Minerall, both againſt inward and outward infirmities, but I freely and willingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime from them all, (eſpecially for Inward cauſes) ſaving onely the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus,</hi> and what may be conveniently prepared out of the ſame, ſaying with learned and conſcionable <hi>Duncanus, Caetera ſciens omitto, tanquam pernitioſa medicamenta, Iatroch. Born. pag.</hi> 91. contenting my ſelfe with that, which by the authoritie and teſtimony of the learned, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments of my worthy friends, and by common practice and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall be (by Gods grace) invincibly confirmed. The firſt corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of my building ſhall be that of <hi>Duncanus,</hi> confirmed alſo by labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and learned <hi>Milius, Hic Regulus eſt ſummum au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i examen, ac vera omnium florum, &amp; tincturarum medicinalium, in Antimonio exiſtentium materia,</hi> that is, this <hi>Regulus</hi> is the chiefeſt examination of gold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the true ſubject and matter of all medicinall vertues, contained within the body of Antimony. To this agreeth the teſtimony of <hi>Baſilius Valentinus Monachus,</hi> calling it <hi>Regulus, ſive Dominus medicinae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divine Authoritie, Nature, and Experience confirmeth this truth, for as life is hid in man, ſo in all things whether Animal, Vegitable, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, it is inviſibly incentred, and ſo punctually indiſcernable, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the learned Philoſopher <hi>Mich. Sengivodius Polonus,</hi> the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpark is only the 8200. part of any ſubject, admire then the effectuall power of that ſparke of life mentioned in the reſembled muſtard-ſeed, and this to the underſtanding Reader, may give ſome touch, both for the univerſalitie, penetration, and perpetuation of this divine medicine.</p>
            <p>And now having diſcovered my <hi>Materia prima,</hi> I will produce ſuch workmen for the erection of this little Fabrick, ſo well experienced in their profound knowledge, that though by malice and ignorance, they have beene often blamed, they could never bee ſhamed, nor juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and the firſt ſhall be that Orientall Star of Naturall, Spagiricall, and Magnetica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l light and knowledge, <hi>Theophraſtus Paracelſus.</hi> Hee in the ſixth Booke, <hi>tit. De vita longa, pag.</hi> 167. ſaith as followeth. <hi>Quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum Antimonium purgat Aurum, ita purgat etiam corpus, continet enim eſſentiam eam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quae nihilimpuri, relinquit in puro, nec ullus eſt uſque adeò, in ſcriptis Archidoxeos peritus, aut tam inſignis Spagyrus, qui vires &amp; facultates Antimonii, plenè indagare queat. In prima enim Yle, Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium adeo exaltatum, &amp; inter Miner as Elementi Aquae praedeſtinatum eſt, ut facultas, &amp; virtus ejus nullo diſuvio, inſtar caeterorum aquaeorum cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentium imminuta, aut abſorpta ſit, adeòque his omnibus Antimonium longè praeſtat. In praede ſtinatione illud ita ſe habet, ut ſe influentiae accommodet, nulla facultate, aut dote ejus diminuta, aut infirmata, itaque ex omnibus mineralibus ſummi Arcani laudem optinet, hoc ſeipſum purgat, &amp; unà ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum etiam alia, quod ſi nihil boni in ſubjecto reperitur, impurum corpus
<pb facs="tcp:21201:4"/>tranſmutat in purum, ſicut de Lepra notum eſt, &amp;c. Paracelſ. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>De vitae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onga, pag.</hi> 167. Like as Antimony purifieth Gold, ſo doth it alſo cleanſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r purifie the body of man, it containeth that eſſence which will permit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o uncleanneſſe to remaine in that which is pure: neither is there any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne found ſo skilfull in the chiefe ſecrets of Nature, or ſo excellent a Spagyrick, that can finde out fully the vertues and medicinall proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Antimony; It is ſo much exalted in his firſt Being, and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the beginning to excell all other Minerals that are of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of water, that his vertues ſhould be and remaine without waſte, or dimunition for ever: and that it ſhould ſympathize and apply to the celeſtiall influence, ſo to be perpetually ſuſtained in full efficacie, vertue, and effect. Therefore of all Minerals it obtaineth the praiſe of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſecret, It purgeth it ſelfe, and together with him all other bodies, and although it findeth but little which is cleane or pure: it purifieth, cleanſeth, and changeth that uncleane body to be moſt pure and cleane, as it is well knowne by practice and experience made upon leprous perſons.</p>
            <p>And againe, in the ſixth booke, pag. 22. <hi>Quinta eſſentia Antimonii ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenum adimit, pulmonem enim &amp; cor &amp; membra laeprae ſubjecta mundat, cutem &amp; corpus totum purificat, &amp; renovat mirum in modum:</hi> The eſſence of Antimony expelleth poyſon, comforteth the heart, and wonderfully reſtoreth and purifieth the lights, and other parts of the body apt to bee infected therewith. Moreover in the 7. booke, pag. 73.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tanta vis &amp; virtus eſt in Antimonio, ut reſtaurat enim &amp; renovat uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſas in corpore vires, ac facultates mirifice:</hi> Such and ſo great is the vertue of Antimony, that it wonderfully reſtoreth and reneweth all the ſtrength and vigour of the whole body.</p>
            <p>And in the eighth booke hee declareth at large the ſeverall vertues and medicinall operations of many other excellent Vegitables and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, and in the end concludeth, <hi>Haec junctim uno in Antimonio latent;</hi> Theſe that we have ſeverally ſpoken of are all incluſively contained in Antimony alone.</p>
            <p>In the ſixth Booke: pag. 22. He teacheth how by their excellencie in vertue and operation, to diſtinguiſh of the preheminence, and degrees of dignities of ſimples, the one above the other, ſaying that thoſe that performe the more difficult and deſperate cures, ought to beare away the glorie of their excelling vertue, concluding thus: <hi>Hoc videmus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidere Antimonio, curat Leproſos, Morpheam, Alopeciam &amp; ſimilia, Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies omnes, &amp; cicatrices, Leoninam, Elephantiam, Tiriam, &amp;c. Et iterum, Antimonium lepram expectit, magis quam de i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſo credibile ſit, non ſecus etiam de aliis intelligendum.</hi> This we ſee to happen in Antimony, it cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth leproſie, cleereth the complexion, ſtayeth the falling of the haire,
<pb facs="tcp:21201:5"/>cureth ring-wormes, tetters, and ſcurvineſſe of the skin, all ſcabs and ſpreading ſores, and all contagious and infectious diſeaſes. And againe afterwards, Antimony expelleth the leproſie more effectually than would bee beleeved, the like operation it hath againſt other deſperate diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>And in the third Boake, pag. 343. <hi>Antimonium nihil finit putreſcere:</hi> Antimony ſuffereth nothing to corrupt or putrifie within the body of man. And in the fourth Booke, pag. 265. <hi>Ita Antimonium per tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes rerum preparatum eſt, eoque reductum ut in dulcedinem abierit, haec ab infantibus lincta, Caducum ſanavit, in Antimonio vis ac tam potens Arcanumlatet, ut paroxyſmum etiam vehementiſſimum tollit:</hi> Antimony is ſo to be prepared, and brought to that ſweetneſſe that it may bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of infants, and have beene thereby cured of the falling ſickneſſe, there is ſo great vertue and power in Antimony, that it taketh away and preventeth the moſt extremeſt fits of the falling ſickneſſe, <hi>Paracelſ. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 265.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, he in the ſixth Booke, pag. 146. ſaith; <hi>Sicut Antimonium finit Aurum, ſie eadem ratione ac forma finit corpus: In illo enim eſt eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, quae nihil impuri cum puro confundi ſinit, atque adeò virtus permanſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ita ut ſeſe ex influentia ſemper dirigat, neque aliud de vi; ac virtute nativa unquam deceſſerit. Meritò igitur omnia, quae mineralium ſunt, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſummum, ac potiſſimum Arcanum in ſe claudit Antimonium, huic uni tribuimus, mundat feipfum unà cum reliquis quae immunda ſunt, porrò ſi nihil omninò ſani adeſt, immundum corpus in mundum transformat: Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>De vitalonga, pag.</hi> 146.</p>
            <p>Like as Antimony refineth Gold, ſo alſo by the ſame reaſon and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner it purifieth the body of man: In it there is that eſſence that ſuffereth no impuritie nor uncleanneſſe to remaine confuſedly intermingled amongſt the pure and good, and his vertues ſo conſtantly remaineth, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting himſelfe alwayes according to the heavenly influence, that of his naturall vertue and power, he ſhall at no time ſuffer loſſe or diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. Worthily therefore doe wee attribute to this alone, the power and vertue of all Minerals, whoſe chiefe and moſt powerfull ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret effect, Antimony comprehendeth in it ſelfe alone, hee refineth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and purifieth together with it ſelfe, what hee findeth uncleane: moreover, though hee finde little or nothing ſound, hee altereth and changeth that impure body to a cleane and ſound conſtitution: <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. And to conclude, <hi>Eſſentia Antimonii est purgatio vera, quae purgat homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem excellentiſſimè ſuperalia quaevis Arcana, radicitus evellit auferendum, ac omne quod immundum eſt: huma num corpus in ſupremum uſque ſanatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis gradum purum efficit, ac ab omnibus aegritudinibus mundat, etiam illis ex quibus oriuntur ulcera; quicquid penes hominem fuerit impuri delet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:5"/>
            <p> The eſſence of Antimony is a true and naturall purge, which purgeth man moſt excellently above all other ſecrets, it utterly taketh away by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e root whatſoever is foule, unwholſome, and ought to be removed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>duceth the body of man to the higheſt degree of perfect health, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eanſeth from all manner infirmities and diſeaſes, even from thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e the originall and fountaine of ulcerous and dangerous diſeaſes, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lly and freely removeth all corrupt and impure humours, that might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e lurking within any part of the body of man. Thus farre <hi>Paracelſus</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his leſſer Chyrurgerie, <hi>pag.</hi> 323.</p>
            <p>My ſecond teſtimony ſhall bee <hi>Martinus Rulandus,</hi> a man of ſound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dgement, great practice and experience, he called the infuſion of this Cup his <hi>Aqua Benedicta,</hi> In the 5. Cent. and the 95. Cure he ſaith thus. <hi>Communi opinione Hermeticorum receptum eſt, Magneſiam Saturni, quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iunt eſſe Antimonium, exiſtere Ens, &amp; raedicem omnium metallorum, ex Regulo hujus Antimonii vaſculum formetur ad uſum medicinale ſatis aptum, mirabile &amp; idoncum ſemper permanens citra ponderis ſui viriumque amiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is received by the conſent and common opinion of all Hermeticall Philoſophers, that the Magneſia of <hi>Saturne,</hi> which they call Antimony, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the originall and beginning of all metals. Of the <hi>Regulus</hi> of this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony there is made a little veſſell or cup verie admirable, fit and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall for his medicinall vertues, alwayes remaining in force without loſſe of waight and vertue: the Infuſion of this Cup he calleth his <hi>Aqua benedicta,</hi> which he alwayes, <hi>(cum maxima aegrotorum ſalute, in omnibus morbis vulgo etiam incurabilibus,)</hi> uſed with good ſucceſſe, and the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the health of his patients, yea alſo in ſuch diſeaſes as were commonly reputed to bee incurable. And in another place hee ſaith; <hi>Miriſicas poſſidet virtutes in tota bene medendi ratione, &amp;c.</hi> It containeth admirable vertues fit to be uſed in all ſound and perfect medicinall cures, 1. It cleanſeth the ſtomack: 2. Purgeth the head: 3. Preventeth the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargie, Swimming, and Vertigo: 4. Cureth frenſie and madneſſe: 5. Preventeth, and many times cureth the falling ſickneſſe. 6. It cureth an inveterated cough and hoarſneſſe, although it bee of long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: 7. Cleareth the winde-pipe and paſſage from the lungs and ſo helpeth ſuch as are ſhort-winded: 8. It cureth the Squinancie or ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in the throat: 9. It openeth, purgeth, and healeth all Impoſtumes in the lungs: 10. Reſtoreth the ſtomack, and expelleth all evill affects of the ſame: 11. Preventeth and cureth the Pleuriſie: 12. Cureth deepe melancholy and madneſſe, cheeres up the heart and vitall ſpirits: 13. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Hypochondriaca or windy melancholy: 14. And is of excelling vertue againſt all manner of Fevers and Agues: 15. It prevents the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the plague, or other contagious diſeaſes: 16. It preſerveth
<pb facs="tcp:21201:6"/>from the Gout, and everie kinde and ſpecies thereof: 17. It purifie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the bloud, cleanſeth the whole body: 18. Diſſipateth and bringeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> way tongealed or clotted bloud, or any other corrupt matter: 19. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſtroyeth and expelleth all manner of wormes: 20. Cureth <hi>Morbus Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>licus,</hi> and <hi>Lues venerea:</hi> 21. It prevaileth againſt the yellow Jaundiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and all overflowings of the gall: 22. It openeth and cleanſeth all man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of obſtructions, it is ſaith <hi>Rulandus, Medicina medicinarum,</hi> the Me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicine of Medicines, good, healthfull, and profitable to be uſed again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all manner of diſeaſes and infirmities whatſoever, this much and much more <hi>Mar. Rulandus</hi> affirmeth upon his experience and knowledge whereof read more, <hi>Ruland.</hi> Cent. 5. Cur. 95. and Cent 9. cap. 51. <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citan</hi> confirmeth everie particular hereof, and reciteth many other ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>periments of his owne practice. See <hi>Pharm. reſtitutae Quercitani, pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 345. and againe <hi>pag.</hi> 238.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martinus Rulandus affirmavit ſe, ſua aqua benedicta. i. Infuſione Regul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Antimonii, centies ſaeliciſſimo ſucceſſu, luem veneream curaſſe:</hi> that is, <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landus</hi> affirmeth, that he (with his bleſſed water which is the infuſed li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor in the Antimoniall Cup) hath perfectly cured the French Pox<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and running of the reines an hundred times, with happie and good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. This reciteth <hi>Quercitan,</hi> out of <hi>Martinus Rulandus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third place I will produce <hi>Quercitan</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Aqua benedicta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Antimonii, Inſigues enim, &amp; mirandas edit effectus, blande provocat vomi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tum, &amp; quatuor vel quinque ſedes, evacuando perſuperiora &amp; inferiora ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul, quod vix praeſtabit alind remedium, uſurpatur etiam foeliciſſime, ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omnis generis febres, etiam peſtiferas: pleuritides item, alioſque de plora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimos affectus, qui ob radices profundius, validiuſque infixas, vix ſubigi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; edom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ripoſſunt: Vid. Quer. Pharm. reſt.</hi> 238.</p>
            <p>The bleſſed water or infuſion of the Antimoniall Cup, performeth moſt excellent and wonderfull effects, it gently procureth vomit, and foure or five ſtooles, purging both upwards and downewards together, which hardly any other medicine will doe: it is adminiſtred verie ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefully againſt all kinde of Fevers, although they be peſtilent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious, alſo againſt the Pleuriſie, and againſt all other deplored and deſperate diſeaſes, which are ſo ſtrongly confirmed, and deeply rooted, that they cannot be over-maſtered any other way, or by any other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines. Thus far <hi>Quercitan</hi> in his <hi>Pharmacop.</hi> reſt. pag. 238.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, this truth ſhall be further confirmed by the teſtimonies of that excellent and learned Doctor of Phyſick and Philoſophie, that wrote out of his owne experience and manuall practice, <hi>Baſilica Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monii,</hi> in the 22. and 23. page he ſaith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antimonium eſt laudabile, &amp; ſingulare Peſtis preſervativum, in Hydrope, Lue peſtifera, &amp; gallica, in Obſtructionibus hepatis, &amp; Lyenis, Ictero, Lepra
<pb facs="tcp:21201:6"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>que ſpeciebus omnibus, medicamen eſt ſpeciale, &amp; admirabile, ad arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum gravitatem à Podagra vel Lue venerea relictam commendatur, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pſa ſanguificatione in Cache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia, &amp; Lepralaudatur, Catarybos cor, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ones ferientes, cum ſummo ſucceſſu exhaurit, &amp; ex hoc celeberrima aqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>almica paratur, ad nubeculas &amp; ſuffuſiones commendatur, &amp; ad pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tia Enemeta cum bono, &amp; foelici ſucceſſu recipitur, curat omnes obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes viſcerum, à quartana &amp; tertiana liberat, in Anaſarca commendabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xiſtit, ſanguinis eſt depurativum, Leproe, Epilepſiae, &amp; Podagrae unicum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſervativum</hi> That is,</p>
            <p>Antimony is a laudable and ſingular preſervative againſt the plague, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſpeciall and an admirable medicine againſt the Dropſie, the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng of the Reines, and the French Pox, againſt all obſtructions of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver or the Spleene, againſt the intollerable paine of the Arteries and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Joynts, proceeding from the infection of the Pox, it is much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nded and praiſed to purifie and cleanſe the bloud againſt the Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and the evill eſtate of the body: It dryeth up all rheumes and diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns that offend the heart or corrupt the lungs: and of this infuſion is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de a moſt excellent medicine for the eyes: it is alſo adminiſtred with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>od and happie ſucceſſe for purging Cliſters, it cureth all obſtructions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the inward parts; it delivereth from the tertian and quartan fevers, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> commended againſt the Dropſie Anaſarca, it is the beſt purifier of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oud, and is the chiefeſt, and only preſervative againſt the Leproſie, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ilepſie, and the Gout. <hi>Pag.</hi> 22, 23. <hi>uſque ad</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>And againe, the ſame Author in his <hi>Baſilica Antimonii, pag.</hi> 39, 40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>th thus; <hi>Antimonium, Naturam confortando, ſudores movendo, ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mque depurando, tantum inimiciſſimis humanae vitae hoſtibus bellum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xit, ut neque Hydrops, neque Podagra, Arthritis, Gallica Lues. Lepra, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſce affines morbi, contra talem medicinam quicquid moliri auſint:</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ony by comforting Nature, by procuring ſweat, and by purifying of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he bloud, wageth ſuch warre againſt the moſt cruell enemies of mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe, that neither the Dropſie, nor the Gout, nor the <hi>Morbus,</hi> nor the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eproſie, can any thing at all withſtand the effectuall vertue of his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icine, <hi>pag.</hi> 39. And againe, <hi>Antimonium, diaphoreticum eſt utiliſſimum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>od vires conſervando ſudores movet, in peſte &amp; febribus ſurſum &amp; deorſum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ovendo purgat, in Hydrope maxime Arcanum:</hi> Antimony is a moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>table ſweat-procuring medicine, which by preſerving the naturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rength procureth ſweat, and purgeth away the infection of the plague <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd peſtilentiall fever by purging the body both upwards and downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. <hi>Ad capit is affectus ſingulare remedium:</hi> It is a ſingular remedy againſt all evill affects of the head Moreover, in the 43. page hee ſaith, <hi>Antimonium per vomitum, ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>num recenter aſſumptum, citiſſime ejicitur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n febribus, &amp; capitis doloribus utiliter exhibitur, omnem Epilepſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae fomitem
<pb facs="tcp:21201:7"/>externit, &amp; horribilem iſtum affectum, &amp; hoſtem vitaeque humanae tortor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> omninò expellit, &amp; eradicat, omnem vitioſam colluviem per vomitum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> alvum expellit: pag.</hi> 43.</p>
            <p>Antimony by vomit expelleth poyſon ſpeedily, if lately taken, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> given verie profitably againſt all fevers and infirmities of the head, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſifteth out the unwholſome matter of the falling-ſickneſſe; and utter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> expelleth this cruell torture, and adverſe enemy to the life and heal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of mankinde, alſo it driveth out by vomit and ſiedge all filthy corrup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion and impuritie out of the body of man.</p>
            <p>Furthermore in the 46. page, he ſaith, <hi>Antimonium febres curat, à p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tredine praeſervat, ciborum appetentiam excitat, ventriculum conſtringe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> confortat, omnemque calorem praeter Naturam, in corpore humano ortum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tinguit, epilepſiam curat, calculum frangit, lumbricos enecat, menſes &amp; u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nam nam movet, dolores etiam podagricos exerinſecus adhibita mulcet, &amp; mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> alia in medicina praeſtat, dentium dolorem ſiſtit, Balſamum vitae inſtaura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſanguinem purificat, obſtructiones reſerat, nunquam anbeloſos &amp; aſthmatic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſerit, ſummum ſanguinis mun dificativum, calculum renum &amp; veſicae fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>git &amp; expellit, urinam &amp; ſudores movet, ulcera, fiſtulas, &amp; vulnera à pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tredine conſervat &amp; ſanat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Antimony cureth fevers, preſerveth from putrefaction, procureth ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>petite, comforteth the ſtomack, allayeth all immoderate, &amp; unnatural heat, cureth the falling ſickneſſe, breaketh the ſtone, killeth worme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> procureth urine, and the monthly flowers, aſſwageth the paines of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gout by bathing with the infuſion and externall application, and hath many other medicinall vertues, ſtayeth the paine of the teeth, reſtoreth the Balſame and ſtrength of Nature, purifieth the bloud, openeth ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtructions, forſaketh not to comfort and help the Aſthmaticall, and ſuch as are ſhort-winded, is the chiefe cleanſer &amp; purifier of the bloud, it brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth &amp; expelleth the ſtone, whether it be of the Reines or of the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it procureth urine and ſweat, cureth perfectly ulcers, fiſtula's; and wounds, and preſerveth them from corruption and putrefaction. <hi>Baſilic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Antimonii, pag.</hi> 47, 48, 49.</p>
            <p>I may not omit the teſtimony of that excellent Phyſitian <hi>Oſwaldu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llius</hi> Phyſitian to the Prince of Anhalt, who in his <hi>Baſilica Chimica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pag.</hi> 214. ſaith thus: <hi>Antimonium operatur mirabilia in peſte, in febribut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> acutis, in Mania, in deſirio, in dementiis, faſcinationibus, morbis omnibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in univerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m opit ulatur, epilepſiis &amp; aliis quamplurimis morbit adjuvat per alvum, per ſuperiora, per poros, per inſenſibilem tranſpirationem, noxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pioſe expurgat.</hi> Antimony doth wonderfull things in the preſervation from the plague, in ſharp fevers, againſt madneſſe, forgetfulneſſe, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, witchcrafts, it helpeth in generall againſt all diſeaſes, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth againſt the falling evill, and many other deſperate diſeaſes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:7"/>
            <p> And againe in the 216. page he ſaith; <hi>Mirabilia operatur in Peſte, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>na, hydrope, longis obſir matis morbis, diuturnis putridis febribus, cache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a, melancholia, inſania, delirio venenorum hauſtorum ſymptomatibus;</hi> It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orketh wonderfull effects againſt the Plague, the Quartan Ague, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ropſie, and againſt inveterate and confirmed diſeaſes, and againſt con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nuall, rotten, and corrupt fevers, againſt the leproſie, and foule ſpots <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the skin, againſt melancholy, madneſſe, dotage, forgetfulneſſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll evill qualities of poyſons and venomous things: And concludeth in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e 219. page, <hi>Non datur melius catharticum:</hi> A better purging medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine cannot be given.</p>
            <p>I will conclude this Diſcourſe with the authoritie and teſtimony of <hi>Mylius,</hi> and <hi>Duncanus Bornetus Iatrochimia, Dun. p.</hi> 93.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antimonium eſt praeſtantiſſimum, &amp; nunquam ſatis laudatum medice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entum, ad reſtaurationem &amp; renovationem corporis humani, tinctur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la expurgat atrum ſanguinem, &amp; vitioſos quoſque humores, idque cum eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uatione manifeſta, &amp; pravorum humorum correctione, hepatis obſtructio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibus opitulatur, hydropem diſcutit, icteritiam curat, laeticiam generat, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſis ſanitatem reſtituit, &amp; est praeſtantiſſimus adpulmones Balſamus: eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue efficax ad Luem veneream curandam, medicamentum. Maximum enim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rolepra Arcanum est, quo nibil fere in hoc morbo praeſtantius inveniri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>est: Lieuem rectificat, matricis dolorem ſedat, menſes movet, ejuſque vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em conſervat, Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phaeam curat, Scorbuto medetur, bilem utramque ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ellit ex toto corpore, calculos frangit, caput &amp; cerebrum expurgat, epilepſiae &amp; convulſionibus omnibus medetur: &amp; ut brevibus dicam in deploratiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is morbis fere omnibus ſummum est remedium:</hi> That is,</p>
            <p>Antimony is a moſt excellent and never-ſufficiently praiſed medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine: for the reſtauration and renovation of the body of man, the infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or tincture thereof purgeth blacke bloud and choller, and everie corrupt humour, and that both by manifeſt evacuation and correction of evill humours: it helpeth againſt all obſtructions of the Liver, and of the Spleene, diſperſeth the Dropſie, cureth the Jaundiſe, procureth cheerefulneſſe and gladneſſe of the heart, reſtoreth the Leprous to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect health, and is the beſt preſervative of the lungs: it is a perfect &amp; an effectuall cure for <hi>Morbus Gallicus,</hi> and the chiefeſt ſecret againſt Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, for that no thing is found to be more excellent againſt that ſoule diſeaſe, it rectifieth the Spleene, aſſwageth the griefes of the Mother, procureth the monethly tearmes, preſerveth and encreaſeth Nature in ſtrength, cureth the Morphew, healeth the Scurvie, expelleth both black and yellow choller out of the body, breaketh and expelleth the ſtone: purgeth the head and braine, helpeth againſt the falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and all convulſions: and to conclude, it is a chiefe and an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent medicine againſt all deſperate and dangerous diſeaſes. Thus farre <hi>Duncanus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:8"/>
            <p> To the end that it may apparantly, and without contradiction be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to all, that theſe collections and teſtimonies grounded upon know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, practice and experience, and all the afore-mentioned Medicina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vertues, are truly and really appropriate to the uſe and vertue of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Antimoniall Cup, being rightly prepared and made of the pure Eſſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Regulus</hi> of Antimony, I will conclude with the teſtimony of <hi>Mili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Duncanus</hi> in theſe words: <hi>Regulus Antimonii, est ſummum Auri ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>enae vera omnium florum, &amp; tincturarum medicinalium, in Antimonie e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentium materia Iatrochim. Dunc. pag.</hi> 91. The <hi>Regulus</hi> of Antimony <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the beſt and chiefeſt examination of gold, it is the true matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of all medicinall vertues, properties, and qualities contained within the body of Antimony.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_books">
            <head>Such as deſire to be further ſatisfied may read,</head>
            <list>
               <item>Baſilica Antimonii.</item>
               <item>Baſilica Chimica Mylii.</item>
               <item>Anatomia Antimonii.</item>
               <item>Baſilica Chymica Crollii.</item>
               <item>Rulandus <hi>at large.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Quercitanus.</item>
               <item>Iatrochimica Duncan.</item>
               <item>Tyr. Ch. Beguin.</item>
               <item>Curriculum Chymicum.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="directions">
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:8"/>
            <head>The manner how to make uſe of the Antimoniall Cup.</head>
            <p>TAke a well-glaſed earthen pot, and put this Cup therein, and powre within and round about it, as much Claret wine, or White <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne. Muſcadell (or Malmeſey if it may be gotten, for it is beſt of all) or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Ale, and let it ſtand ſo warme as you may well endure your finger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one houre or more, and let it be kept reaſonable warme, at the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neere the ſame degree of warmneſſe by the fire cloſe covered in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hole, by the ſpace of twelve houres: and afterwards a Cupfull or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore taken faſting in the morning, purgeth the body from whatſoever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> offenſive to Nature: the operation is gentle and without any violence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> danger, as hath beene oftentimes proved: let them governe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lves as after other Phyſick.</p>
            <p>By the quantitie and proportion of Wine or Ale (a pint for two, or for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ree) you may prepare for as many as you pleaſe at one time: but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are no more than you will ſpend that morning, for by ſtanding it alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth his qualitie and nature.</p>
            <p>For the manner of the operation, it is difficult to fore-know, for it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>perateth according as it is moſt convenient and neceſſarie for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent eſtate and conſtitution of the body, ſometimes and in ſome conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utions, it operateth by Vomit alone, in ſome others by Siedge alone, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thers by urine and ſweat, but moſt commonly it worketh all theſe waies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et without violence or danger.</p>
            <p>If you deſire it ſhould operate rather by Siedge, you muſt uſe Ale, or Malmeſey which is beſt, or elſe Muſcadell: for white and Claret wines, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re more apt for vomits of their owne ſelfe naturall properties: Some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe to drinke poſſet drinke, to haſten and facilitate the operation which you may doe, but I rather approve the operation of it alone, for then you ſhall better ſee and judge what offendeth your body, by that which Nature will expell; if you finde not your ſelfe afterwards more hungrie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ively, and cheerfull, beleeve me not.</p>
            <p>You are to obſerve that according to the qualitie of the heat, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the infuſion, and the quantitie you give, you may make it fit for any, from the tender infant, to the ſtrongeſt conſtitution.</p>
            <p>Give to women and children halfe a cupfull or a cupfull according to the age and ſtrength: if it worke not effectually to your liking, you muſt make it hotter, and drinke more the next time.</p>
            <p>To prevent ſickneſſe, once or twice in the Spring and Autumne, or once in a moneth will be ſufficient, for ordinarie infirmities, take it three times, leaving a day or two betwixt, but for confirmed diſeaſes it ſhould be taken as often as it worketh, for when it hath vanquiſhed and expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the enemies of Nature, and prevailed againſt all the impurities of the body, it is at peace with all that is pure and good, and then will in
<pb facs="tcp:21201:9"/>work no more, &amp; thereby you may be well aſſured that you are perfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> well, and this I do affirme upon mine owne knowledge, practice and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to be true, &amp; if any man make doubt of the waſte &amp; diminuti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the medicinall vertues of this Cup through uſe, let them bee aſſured they will never decay; for teſtimony whereof I have made continuall uſe of one Cup for above three yeeres paſt, and I finde it more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all everie time than other: and the Right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>Thomas Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleton</hi> Knight hath made more experience hereof, and I am certaine will be ready and forward to confirme the ſame. When you have made uſe of this Cup: drie it with a faire cloth, and ſo put it up ſafe into his bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for by waſhing it unheedfully or ſcouring it you may waſte the metall, or break the Cup: for it is brittle like glaſſe, but if any ſuch miſchance do happen let them reſerve the metall, &amp; bring it to me in weight, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any commixture, and for ten ſhillings I will give them a new Cup.</p>
            <p>And if any through ignorance, or malice, or ſuch others that regard their particular lucre and profit more than the health and generall good of their Chriſtian brethren, ſhall unjuſtly report that this Antimoniall Cup is either counterfet, and of verie little or no vertue at all, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe dangerous, pernicious, and hurtfull, as being compoſed of <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and Poiſons, and the like; as for the vertue and continuance, it hath been already ſufficiently proved: To prevent the calumny of the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer though it be an Herculean labour, yet to preſerve my reputation immaculate, as much as in me lyeth, I doe confeſſe unto you really, it is made of the Mercurie of Antimony, which is the pure ſpirit, ſoule, and life of the Minerall, refined, ſeparated, and prepared from all impurities with much diligence, care, labour, and charges, but that it containeth any of that <hi>Mercury</hi> which is common Quickſilver, or <hi>Mercury</hi> ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, which is made of Quickſilver and poyſonfull Arſenick, or elſe <hi>Mercury</hi> precipitate, which is alſo made of Quickſilver, and the Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive <hi>Aqua-fortis</hi> or <hi>Regis:</hi> I doe ſincerely and truly proteſt in the faithfull word of a Miniſter and Preacher of the ſacred Goſpell of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, there is none of theſe contained in any that I make, neither any thing elſe, but what I am perſwaded in my conſcience, and have found by experience upon my ſelfe, my friends, my neighbours, and mine owne children, to bee for the health, good, and benefit of the body of man, and this I confirme to be the ſincere truth, as I ſhall anſwer to the Lord Jeſus at the latter day: And ſo I conclude, and commend it and you to the bleſſing of our Great, Glorious, and Eternall God, to whom together with his true and only Sonne, and the moſt holy and bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> three powerfull Perſons, but one immortall God, bee given and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> creatures, all honour, praiſe, and glorie, world with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21201:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
